Hello everyone. Can you hear me?
>> We hear you.
Wait a few seconds and
All right, I'll wait for a couple of
seconds and then we'll start.
Okay, let's begin.
So, welcome to this third lecture
uh in our series of lectures on deep
learning.
Today, we're going to begin our lecture
series on training neural networks. So,
here are the topics we're going to
cover. We're going to talk about the
problem of learning.
We're going to talk about the perceptron
rule for learning individual perceptrons
and its in applicability to multi-layer
perceptrons. We'll briefly mention
greedy solutions for classification
networks. I won't actually go over
those, but the material is in the slides
and will appear in the quiz and we're
going to introduce the notion of
learning through empirical risk
minimization. Then in the next class,
we're going to go more into erm and
we'll talk about function optimization,
gradient descent and so on.
So here's what we know so far.
Neural networks are universal
approximators. They can model any
boolean function. They can model any
classification boundary. They can model
any continuous valued function so long
as they have the minimal architecture
needed to model the function.
So as we saw in the last class, these
boxes which represent various uh AI
tasks
uh these are functions.
So for example in speech recognition a
voice signal goes in a transcription
comes up there's something in the middle
that thing is a function that operates
on the voice signal to generate the
transcription an image captioner
operates on the image to generate
generate the caption. So again it's a
function that takes an image as an input
and outputs a caption for the game
states. the uh neural network is a
function that takes in a game state and
predicts the next move or more recently
when you're speaking about LLMs and such
like uh the neural network is a function
that takes in a prompt and generates a
response. So in every case it's a
function and uh we know that these
functions can be approximated by neural
networks.
But then we must begin considering the
mechanics of it. The network as a
function operates on numbers. It's a
mathematical object. It takes in
numbers. It outputs numbers. So for it
to perform all the tasks we saw, all the
inputs and outputs we saw, the voice
signal and its transcription, the image
and its caption, the game state and the
next game state, the prompt and
response, they must all somehow be
represented as numbers. Otherwise you
can't have a mathematical operation on
it.
So our first question is how do we
represent these things as numbers in
general? How do we represent the input
to the network and how do we represent
the output of the network?
Also we know that the network as a
universal approximator can compute
functions that perform all these tasks.
But how actually do we compose the
network that performs these functions?
So first we're going to compose con
consider the second issue. We'll get
back to the issue of representing an
input representing inputs and outputs
later.
So let's begin by looking at the basic
units of our network. The perceptron.
Here's the perceptron. It operates on
real value inputs and computes an aphine
function of the inputs which is a
weighted sum of all the inputs plus a
bias bias. This aphine term which we
will generally represent as Z in our
lectures is then put run activation
function. The basic activation function
that we saw in the earlier classes was a
threshold activation but in reality it
can be any other function. So uh it
could be for example a sigmoid or a relu
or a soft plus and the output of the
perceptron is the output of this
activation function. The parameters of
the perceptron are these weights and the
bias. You you determine how the
perceptron behaves by modifying the
weights and the bias.
Now just a shortcut instead of having an
explicit bias like so we can also think
of the neuron I'm going to arbitrarily
call these units ei
as having one more additional input
component whose values fixed to one and
now the bias term simply becomes the
weight of this extra term. So this is a
little more convenient representation
because what was a aine combination
becomes a linear combination in this
representation and so there's some
there's some uh there's some better
intuition when we work with linear
combinations also in general when I draw
networks very often I don't explicitly
draw the bias term so you must assume
implicitly that there is an extra input
peg to one that captures the bias.
The entire network of course is a
network of perceptrons. We'll assume
feed forward networks which means that
computations are performed in a strictly
directed way proceeding unidirectionally
from the input to the output left to
right in this figure. When we process an
input each neuron is computed exactly
once. This means the output of the
neuron does not directly or indirectly
ever feed back to the input.
Now a major part of designing these
networks is the architecture of the
network. The number of layers, the
number of neurons in each layer, how
they are connected and so on. For now,
I'm going to assume that the
architecture of the network is given to
us and is capable of representing
whatever function we want the network to
model.
So the entire network is a function. It
takes an input, it produces an output.
The parameters of the function are the
weights and the biases of the neurons in
the network which are represented by the
blue arrows in this figure. So we can
represent the function mathematically
like so. the function that's uh uh
computed by the network in this manner.
We can we can write it as f of x
semicolon w. x is the input. f of course
is the function and the term that
appears after the semicolon the w
represents the network parameters. This
is a standard representation where you
separate the input from the parameters
by a semicolon.
to model any specific function with a
network, we just need to modify these
parameters appropriately for it. So when
we speak of learning a network, we are
speaking of learning the weights and
biases, basically this W term, such that
the network computes the desired
function. And so having set these basics
in place, I'm going to pause a couple of
minutes for any questions before moving
on. Do we have any questions?
>> Hi, Professor. Yeah,
>> I want to ask will the weight be
provided or it is calculated by the
model.
>> So the weights are now by modifying the
weights the model computes different
functions. So this lecture and then the
rest of the next the next six lectures
are all about how you obtain these
weights.
Any other questions?
Okay. Was everything I mentioned so far
clear to everybody? Just give me a
thumbs up or a yes so I can move on.
Okay, that's one yes. That's
representing the entire class. Okay, a
few more thumbs ups. Okay,
>> there's a lot of thumbs up.
>> Thank you. All right, you can count
them. Anyways, so let's continue. Right,
we know the MLP can represent anything.
So we know that given any function at
all we can construct an MLP that
computes it. But then the question is
how do we construct this MLP? Now one
solution of course is to try to
construct it by hand. Say for example we
want to construct an MLP to compute this
diamond shaped decision boundary over
two dimensional inputs. We can do it
with a network that uses threshold
activations. We can construct a first
perceptron for this boundary here. Now
this is a line with a slope one that
goes through min - 1 0 and 0 1. So if
you write it write write it out as an
equation the the equation for this line
is x1 - x2 + 1 equals 0. And any point
to the right of it if you plug it into
the equation that's going to give you a
positive value. Any point to the left is
going to give you a negative value. So
if I just draw the perceptron out for
this line x1 has a weight of one. X2 has
a weight of minus one and the bias is
one and so you can draw this person. You
can use the same method to capture this
boundary and this boundary and this
boundary and then eventually
uh just add an and perceptron on the top
which compares the sum of the four
outputs to the to the value four and we
get the desired output function. Now
this is handcrafted and the problem is
this kind of handcrafted procedure can
only be used for the simplest problems
for something even slightly more
complex. This is not feasible. So back
to the drawing board
the better option is this. Given a
function g of x that we want to model,
we can derive the parameters of this
network such that this network computes
this function g of x as accurately as
possible. Again, I'm assuming that the
architecture of the network is given and
is capable of computing this function.
So here's how we do it.
you're given the function uh g of x
which I've shown using this dotted line
over here.
Now for any given setting of the weights
W the function of the network computes
some function which depends on W say
this guy right. So you have this shaded
area over here which represents the
error between what the network computes
and what you actually want the network
to compute. And so we want what we want
to do is to train the network to
minimize this shaded area. That make
sense to everybody? Yes. Now
just give me some thumbs up, give some
yeses so I can move on. Right? Okay.
And so that's what we're going to do. We
are going to learn the network weights.
We're going to figure out how to set up
the network weights such that this
shaded area is minimized.
But then for this, in order to be able
to do this, we need to be able to
quantify this shaded area. And to
quantify the shaded area, we need
something. What is it? We need to be
able to quantify this area. Anyone?
What is it? We would need to quantify
this area. An integral. An integral of
what?
What would you need to integrate? a loss
function g of x. Not really. What we
really need is
uh to quantify this area, we first need
to define some way some measure of the
gap between the two. And this is what we
will call the divergence function. The
divergence function is a function of the
actual network output and the value that
you want the network to compute and it
quantifies this gap.
Now the divergence function has the
property that it goes to zero when g of
x exactly equals f and g and f are not
the same. It's always going to be
positive. you want it to always be
positive because if it took both
positive and negative values when you
integrate the positive and negative
values could cancel out. So the
divergence function has the property
that it's always positive and it's equal
to zero when f is exactly equal to g. So
once you define a divergence function of
that kind then this entire shaded area
is going to be the integral of the
divergence function over the entire
input and we are going to try to train
the network to minimize this total error
which is the integral of the divergence
function over the entire input.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
So okay beautiful.
Now this is easy.
>> Yeah.
>> So uh I understand that in classical
machine learning model you need uh like
truth value and that will help you to
evaluate the error between the actual
and the predicted. So does that does
this what can I say that the divergence
function here means the truth value or
what please can you share
>> the divergence function is the gap
between the truth value and what the
value what the network computes now when
you say error how do you define error
all of you are probably just thinking of
the squared error but that's just one
way of defining error the term error
itself is very abstract you have to put
a formula to compute the error that
formula what we're going to call the
divergence.
Does that make sense?
>> Yes.
>> Right. And so we're going to integrate
the divergence over the entire input
that gives you this shaded area. You're
going to estimate the W that minimizes
this area. The problem is in order to
compute this integral,
this function g of x must be known
everywhere. It must be fully specified
everywhere. If you already knew G of X,
why would you need a need a neural
network to compute it? You have G of X.
Now, in practice, in reality, when
you're trying to build a network for a
task to compute a function like
classifying patterns, you actually will
not have this entire function g of X to
begin with. What we will have instead
are samples from the function.
basically input output pairs uh that
tell you what the value of the function
is at a bunch of different inputs. And
so these are all you're going to have
these input output pairs. And you're
going to have to learn the network that
computes this entire function from just
these input output pairs. Now where do
these input output pairs come from? It's
just sampling the function. You
literally just collect data from the
real world like images and their class
labels. So speech recordings and their
transcriptions those represent input
output pairs. But then again the thing
you must remember that these input
output pairs represent samples of the
function. And we are trying to estimate
a network that computes this entire
function from just these samples.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right? And so
these samples are what we will call our
uh training functions training samples.
So each sample is going to be consist of
an input x and the actual function value
which I've represented as d to indicate
that as the desired output of the
network. And so now we must learn the
entire function from these few training
samples that we've got. So here is a
simpler 1D visualization of the problem.
We want to learn this function but we
want to learn this function from just
these training samples where for each X
you're given the corresponding function
value. Now we want to actually compute
the entire shaded area but we don't act
we can't compute the shaded area because
we only have these guys. So what we will
do is that we will compute the error at
these training points these distances
and we're going to compute and we will
define what we call an empirical error.
It's empirical it's because it's based
on points that you have actually
observed which is the average divergence
over these training uh samples.
And this
is what we're going to try to minimize
when we train our model. And the hope is
that the average error over these
training samples is a good proxy for the
entire shaded area. Again, what we are
trying to minimize is the shaded area.
Do not forget that. But we are using
this average error over all these
training samples as a proxy because
that's the best we can do. And that's
what we will minimize to to learn the
model. Again, did that make sense? Was
that clear to all of you guys? The
difference between the two things we're
doing, what we want and what we do,
right? Okay, great.
And so when we minimize the error over
these training samples, the assumption,
implicit assumption here is that if we
could somehow push this empirical error
to zero so that we find some network
parameters that that calculate the
output of the function exactly at these
training samples. Then somehow magically
the network will also give you the
correct values at all of these other
points that you have never seen in
training. Now this is not guaranteed at
all. It's more a hope but really this is
the best we can do. So when I speak of
learning the function, we're actually
not speaking of learning this entire
function because we cannot rather what
we are really speaking of is fitting the
function at these points
with the implicit hope that when I do so
the function is correct everywhere else
as well.
And so the story so far is that when we
are speaking of training a neural
network, learning a neural network, this
refers to determining the parameters of
the network, the weights and bias for it
to model a desired function. And the
network must have sufficient capacity to
model the function. Ideally, you would
like to optimize the network to
represent the desired function
everywhere. However, this requires
knowledge of the function everywhere. So
instead we draw input output training
instances from the function and estimate
network parameters to fit the input
output relation at these instances. And
we hope that if we do this it will fit
the function everywhere else as well.
And so that leads us to our first poll.
Let me launch it.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
All right.
So,
let me end this since it's taking me a
minute
and Okay. Does anybody want to answer
that first question? True or false?
>> False.
>> True or false? Right? Because the
network should have sufficient capacity.
What about the next four? The first
statement, true or false?
First statement, true. Okay. Second one,
true or false.
The third one, true or false.
The fourth one, true or false.
Pause. Right. Beautiful. So, everybody
gets Oh, that's right about this. what
we've said so far. So let's continue.
Let's begin with a simple task learning
a classifier. This is simpler than
learning regressions and in fact this
was the earliest problem addressed using
MLPS. We will specifically consider
binary classification though what we
discuss will actually generalize to
multiclass classification.
In binary classification the classifier
assigns one of two class labels either
zero or one to each training instance.
So the actual classification curve that
that uh you want to learn may be
something like this green curve
which says that for all x's in this
region the output is zero. For all x's
in this region the output is one. Now of
course you don't have the entire
function. What you have instead are just
these few training samples and you have
to learn the function from it. Now the
function computed by the network may be
different from the true function. It
could be this dotted line over here. And
so this function
is going to make errors.
The uh on at least some of the training
samples
and when the network output at a
training instance is not the same as the
desired output you have a classification
error. So given this,
what would the obvious metric be to
train this network? What would you want
to minimize? Anyone?
What would you want to minimize
over here? So error, what error?
Empirical error. So for a classification
problem, this is the act that you're
making a certain number of
classification errors, right? And so the
obvious error metric here is going to be
the number of mclassifications, the
number of instances where the network
output does not match the desired
output. This is what you want to
minimize. I have this extra one over
here and here to convert it to the
fraction of training instances that are
mclassified. But anyway, you can focus
on this. You really want to minimize the
total number of best classifications.
And now to do this, let's start with the
original MLP as proposed by Rosenblot.
This is a network of uh threshold
activation perceptrons. We're going to
see how to train this network using only
the training set of input output pairs.
Now rather than this entire network I'm
going to reduce it to the simplest
possible network which is just a single
unit a single perceptron.
So the single perceptron as we know
gives us a heavy side step function.
There is a linear hyper plane given by
z=0 which is to say the aphine uh
function of input summation w i x i + b
equals 0. On one side the output is one.
On the other side the output is zero. So
the complete function computed by the
perceptron is going to look like this
step.
Except when you want to train the
perceptron from the training data.
You're not going to see this entire
function. You're only going to be given
these input output pairs like these blue
and red dots. Each of these dots
represents a training XY pair where X is
the coordinate of the input and Y is the
desired output which is either zero or
one. We must learn the function from
only these pairs. Now the output of the
perceptron is given by this bino
familiar formula which is it is one when
this aphine function of the inputs is
positive and zero otherwise and the
boundary of course is where the aphine
function is exactly equal to zero. Now
learning the perceptron is the same. So
this boundary represents a hyper plane
and so learning the perceptron is the
same as learning this hyper plane which
is the same as learning these weights
and this bars.
Now this is an aphine
uh this is written in terms of an aphine
function. For convenience sake I'm going
to restate it in this manner where I
plug in an extra input which is a one
and the weight of that one becomes a
bias. And so when I redo it in this
manner then uh we can restate the
perceptron as saying that the output is
one
when the weighted combination of inputs
is positive and zero otherwise. And
learning the perceptron is refers to
learning these weights such that this
classifier
uh has the fewest errors.
Now, so in order to find the perceptron,
what we really want to do is to find the
equation of this hyper plane such that
all the positive red dots lie on one
line on on one side of the line and all
the blue dots. So the red and blue dots
over here are refer to the two classes
and you want to find the hyper plane
such that all the red dots lie on one
side of the line and all the blue dots
lie on the other side. Now here I'm
making an assumption that there is
actually a hyper plane that can separate
the red and blue dots. When such a hyper
plane exists then the two classes are
set to be linearly separable because
they can be separated by a hyper plane
which is obtained from a linear equation
or an fine equation. So we're going to
consider the linearly separable case
first.
Uh so
is this making sense the setup over here
so far?
Okay. Now
before we continue, let's see how the
classification rule works.
The classification rule basically says
that the weighted sum of inputs
is zero at the boundary. Right? That's
the boundary. Now I can write the
weights as a single vector W in this
manner where W is simply the set of
weights W1 through WN.
The inputs in turn can be written as a
vector
X1 through XN. So when I say wrpose
when I say summation wi xi= 0
this is the same as saying wranspose x
equals z.
Does everybody agree with this? Is it
this one here? Does everybody agree with
this?
Okay. So when wrpose x is equal zero,
what is the relationship between w and
x?
If the inner product between two vectors
is zero, what is the relationship
between w and x? They are perpendicular
to each other. Right?
So if this vector w
is the vector w, then this hyper plane
is simply the set of all vectors in the
input space that are at 90° to w. So
that's the equation of the hyper plane.
Now if I have some other vector over
here, let's call this X with some angle
theta.
Then what would wranspose X be for
vectors that are not on the hyper plane?
That's simply going to be you're all
familiar from your linear algebraic, you
know, class. It's magnitude of W,
magnitude of X cos theta.
Is everybody familiar with this one over
here? Are you guys familiar with this?
Yes. So
if the vector x is on the same side of
the plane as w, what will cos theta be?
Will it be positive or negative?
If the vector
come on guys,
>> positive.
>> I think it's positive. It's positive
because the angle is less than 90°.
Right?
On the other hand, if the vector x is on
the other side of the so that the angle
is more than 90°, then what is cos
theta?
Negative. So in other words, wrpose x is
going to be greater than zero for all
vectors on this side of the plane and is
going to be less than zero for all
vectors on this side of the plane.
And so
here is a summary of our problem. We
want to find the vector W
such that the plane described by Wrpose
X=0 perfectly separates the data. And
furthermore, Wrpose X is positive for
all the data from the positive class,
all the red dots, and negative for all
the data from the negative class, the
blue dots. So you want to find the
vector w such that wranspose x is
positive for all the red dots and it's
negative for all the blue dots. So is
the problem set up clear to you guys? It
making sense to you guys?
Yes or no?
Okay.
So how do we do this
for linearly separable data? The popular
solution which was originally proposed
by Rosenblot is an online algorithm.
It's a famous perceptron algorithm. It
initializes W and incrementally updates
it each time we encounter an instance
that is incorrectly classified and it's
guaranteed to find the correct solution
for linearly separable data.
So
uh here is the algorithm itself is based
on a very simple principle. So let's say
these are my axes
and this is my let's say this is an
instance of a positive training data X.
So this belongs to the class + one. Now
this data can be correctly classified by
a great many different linear
classifiers. This guy which has this as
a weight. this guy which has this as a
weight and maybe this guy which has this
as a weight. So of all of these guys
which is the classifier
that is most conservative where the
boundary is farthest from this point in
every direction. Which would that one
be? Anyone?
Which would that one be of all the
classifiers? Where must the weight
point?
They're not clear. So
>> the one which points to the point,
>> you'd want something you'd want it to
point exactly at the vector itself
because that's when this thing is
farthest away. Anything else is going to
get closer, right? Anything else is
going to get closer in one direction or
the other. So for positive instances
the ideal weight should be in the same
direction as X. If this were class minus
one where would you want the weight to
be?
If the class were minus one where would
you want it's going to the ideal one
weight is going to be minus X. This make
sense to everybody?
Yes or no? Right. It's so it's a very
beautiful idea. And so this is what
we're going to be uh using for our
perceptron algorithm. The perceptron
algorithm is a very simple learning
rule. You initialize the weights somehow
and then you cycle through the training
instances. If the instance is and check
if the instance is correctly classified
by the current classifier. If the
instance is mclassified
then if the instance is from the
positive class then to the current
weight you add the ideal weight for the
positive instance and we know that for
the positive instance the ideal weight
is the vector itself. So you just do w=
w + x. Basically you're pulling the
weight towards the ideal weight for that
vector. If the instance is from the
negative class once again if it's
mclassified you're going to push the
weight towards the ideal weight for that
vector which is minus x and you're going
which which means you're going to be
subtracting
x from w. So is the rationale behind
this clear to all of you guys?
The logic behind this someone said no.
So what was the doubt here?
Any doubts here?
Is the logic behind this clear?
So
the training data, right? So the
training data is going to be tell you
whether it's positive or negative. So
let so let me uh do this with an
example, right? I have more math, but
I'm going to be W is a weight vector,
right? So I'll skip the math
here. Let's say I have this training
data. These are my red dots from the
positive class and the blue dots from my
negative class. So I just randomly
initialize my weight vector like so. If
I randomly initialize my weight vector
like so, this is going to be my decision
boundary. Everybody good with this so
far?
Yes or no? This is just the
initialization of the algorithm. Okay.
Now I begin testing all my data points
one at a time to see whether the data
instance is correctly classified or not.
And so this is the initialization and I
go through all of my data and I
eventually find that here's a negative
instance and this negative instance is
on the wrong side of the boundary.
Right? What is the ideal weight for this
negative instance? What is the ideal
weight for this negative instance?
Anyone?
What's the ideal weight for this
negative instance? Come on. Minus one.
It's going to be exactly this guy.
Correct. And so I'm just going to be
adding this guy
to this. Basically, I'm dragging this
weight towards this one.
That make sense to all of you guys? And
so that's going to be my new miss
instance. And that's going to give my
new be my new weight. And that's going
to be my new boundary. Now I take this
boundary against all my because if it's
a negative instance, you want the ideal
weight to point away from the instance.
That's what we just discussed, right?
Whereas for a positive instance, you
want the ideal weight to ideally point
towards the instance. So you have this
new classifier, then you check all of
the data points again. Is there a data
point here that's mclassified? Can
anybody see a data point that's
mclassified out here?
>> Yes.
>> Yes. So which one is that? The red one.
Right. So this gu is mclassified. What
is the ideal weight? This is from the
positive class. What's the ideal weight
vector for this instance?
Anyone
+ one?
It's plus x. This is this is going to be
the ideal weight vector for this
instance.
Right? So I'm just going to drag this
guy towards the ideal weight vector for
this instance by adding x. And so now I
have my updated updated weight that
gives me a new decision boundary. And
this new decision boundary is perfect.
It makes no more mistakes. I've got a
classifier, right?
So yeah, this this is
y + x. We just discussed this, right? y
+ x. If I have a data instance over here
and this is my positive class, what is
the best weight for this guy? Tell me
where do you want the boundary to be?
Where do you want the boundary to be for
this guy?
The ideal weight, the ideal boundary for
just this instance is going to be as far
away from it as possible in every
direction, right? Yes or no?
>> Ro, I have a question.
>> Yes. So, so that's at 90° to the sky,
right? Which means because if it's not
far away from it, if I get this guy,
you're using this as a representative.
You expect training data points, your
test data to have some spread around it.
So this is less conservative than this
guy, is it not?
Which is the most conservative
classifier?
This one or this one or this one? Which
is the most conservative classifier?
If I have only one training instance,
then you want the if I think of this as
being representative,
you you got it. You want the farthest
one and the farthest one has a has a
weight pointing directly at the data,
right? That clear to everybody the
logic? And so whenever we whenever we
got a mclassified instance, we just
added the ideal weight for that instance
to the current weight and kept modifying
it and uh you got a new classifier. And
the rule says that if the classes are
linearly separable, this process is
guaranteed to converge in a finite
number of steps.
So
any questions?
there.
>> Oh yes, I have a question on this one.
>> Doing this will it not lead to some kind
of overfitting if we are looking for
like a perfect classification especially
if there is noise in input data.
>> This is the best you can this is the
best you can do with your training data.
There's no notion of overfitting, right?
You're just trying to train a
classifier. You want to build a step
function that that uh
separates the red data from the blue
data as best as it can. Of course,
there's a whole bunch of classifiers
which will do that. It's going to find
one of them, right? So overfitting is a
is beyond that. We just speaking of
building the classifier.
So if there are multiple wrong
classified objects, if the data are
classes are linearly separable, then
this algorithm is going to keep on
adjusting until eventually in a finite
number of steps, it's guaranteed to find
a classifier that actually separates the
classes perfectly.
That answer your question?
There is a theoretical guarantee, right?
Okay. So that's where we are. But that's
only true for linearly separable
classes.
If the classes are not linearly
separable over here like this guy,
right? So Bruno, yes, this is an online
algorithm. Now if the classes are not
linearly separable like in this guy
here, there is no hyper plane that will
cleanly separate the blue and the red
data. Will this algorithm ever converge?
Do you think it'll converge?
>> Yes or no?
>> No.
It should not because there will always
be an error. It's just going to keep
going on and on and on and on and on.
And so now let's look at a more complex
problem. I just looked at a single
perceptron. But then let's look at the
more complex problem of uh this guy,
this double pentagon. Right? Now here we
want to learn an MLP for this
classification boundary on 2D inputs. We
want the net output of one in the yellow
regions and zero outside. But we are not
given the actual boundary. We're only
given this training data which are the
red and the blue dots. Now we know that
this decision boundary can be perfectly
represented by this network with with an
appropriate choice of weights.
We saw this we already saw this in the
past couple of classes. So the question
is even given this network with a
perfect architecture for this problem
can we learn its parameters to represent
this fun this function from the training
data using the perceptron algorithm. Now
to learn this pattern perfectly we want
to learn the this guy this these five
neurons must learn these five boundaries
for the lower uh pentagon. These five
guys must learn these five boundaries
for the second pentagon. These two guys
must learn to and this one and this one
respectively. And this must learn to
order the outputs of the two. Only when
it does that will this network learn
this decision boundary perfectly.
That clear to everybody? That's what we
want to learn, right? Yes. No.
Okay.
So, we know it's possible. For
simplicity, I'm going to assume that all
of these other neurons are perfectly
trained. We've learned somehow
successfully. Some oracle came by and
gave us the correct parameters for all
of these neurons. This neuron is the
only one whose weights and bias remain
to be learned. So, we know that that
neuron must capture this boundary,
right?
But the labels we have in the training
data those things are going to be this
combination of red and blue. So can we
learn this boundary from these labels
data? What do you think? Can we learn
that boundary? Yes or no? Right? No.
Right? Because why
why can we not?
because the classes are not linearly
separable. You can only learn the
boundary if the classes are linearly
separable. So that leads us to our next
poll.
Let's go back and poll two.
Okay, 15 seconds, guys.
Okay,
give you five more and let me end this
part.
Okay.
Uh
for the first question, what's the
answer? Yes or no?
No. Second question
both perfect right let's check so
no for the first one and yes both are
true the perceptron will need relabeling
the data to make them linearly separable
if you want to learn the boundary and so
here
can a linear classifier learn this
boundary can a perceptron learn this
boundary from this data no because The
data are not linearly separable. We can
only learn a linear classifier perfectly
if the data are linearly separable. And
these dots are not linearly separable.
If we use the labels that were given to
us as part of the training data. So to
learn this line, we will actually
require linearly separable labels of
this kind. But
how do we know which instances to
reabel? Right? So I mean this means that
we're going to have to releabel some of
the data, right? But how will we know
which instances to reabel so that we
actually get data that are linearly
separable that give us this boundary and
that complete the overall uh double
pentagon pattern? How do we know this?
Can you guess how do we decide which
instances to reabel?
Clearly we have to re label the
instances to learn the boundary. Which
ones do we do? Which ones to be rele?
So maybe I'll give you five seconds more
for a guess.
Okay.
So
next.
So it turn it turns out that the only
way to do this is to actually try every
possible way of relabeling the data
until we find a linearly separable
relabeling such that when we learn the
label line with it the overall network
classifies all training points
correctly. So even when you want have to
learn just a single line and you're
given the rest of the network, we have
to try out every possible way of
releabing releabeling the training
instances. And if you have n training
instances, how many different ways of
releabeling exist that you must test?
Anyone with n training instances, how
many how two ra to n, right? It's
impossible. It's 2 to n. And so this is
for one line. Now imagine that you have
to learn the full problem. Every neuron
has to be uh learned. This means that
you're going to have to try every
possible way of relabeling all the data
for every one of these neurons such that
the entire network composite network
computes the correct uh double pentagon
decision boundary. And this is not going
to be feasible. It's an exponential
search over inputs. And so here is the
situation we have.
If we try to learn this entire network
using the perceptron algorithm, even if
our network has the perfect architecture
of the problem, we know need to know the
desired output for every neuron. And the
desired output such that should be such
that each neuron by itself has a
linearly separable task. But together
these linear separators compute a double
pentagon decision value. So we need to
determine the correct releabeling the
correct set of desired outputs for every
neuron in the network uh in addition to
the weights of the network. And if you
re label just one of these points
wrongly for just one of the neurons, the
entire network is going to be useless.
And so training this network using the
perceptron
uh learning rule is a combinatorial
optimization problem. As part of the
problem, we must now also determine the
correct output for each neuron for every
training instance. This is at least
exponential time complexity.
And so the perceptron rule cannot
directly be used to learn an MLP. We end
up with the exponential complexity of
assigning intermediate labels even if
the classes are separable and our
network structure is perfect for it. It
gets even worse when the classes are not
actually separable. So as a workaround
uh Bernie Widro proposed a greedy
algorithm which uses greedy search to
learn the perceptrons. The algorithm to
learn a single perceptron was called
Adelene and the MLP extension of it was
called Medline. They are both very
pretty algorithms. They're explained on
the slides. I'm not going to mention
them and discuss them in class. Uh I do
have one gripe about Bernie Vidro. Uh he
took he stole two of my best students
some 10 years ago. Anyways,
and so
uh here's a story so far.
Learning a network is the same as
learning the weights and biases to
compute a target function
which will require a network with
sufficient capacity. In practice, we
learn the networks by fitting them to
match the input output relationship of
training instances drawn from the target
function.
uh a linear decision boundary can be
learned by a single peretron with a
threshold activation in linear time
if the classes are linearly separable.
Nonlinear decision boundaries require
networks of perceptrons and training an
MLP with threshold function threshold uh
activation perceptrons will require
knowledge of the input output
relationship for every training instance
for every perceptron in the network.
These must be determined as part of the
training. And so for threshold
activations, this is an NP complexity
combinatorial optimization problem
without a real good solution. So did all
of that make sense so far? Any
questions? First, did that make sense?
Why we cannot learn the use the
perceptron rule to train an MLP?
Right.
And
any questions? Any
questions?
Okay, I'm assuming there are no
questions. Okay, may I continue?
All right, I'll just take that for a
yes.
So once people discovered that training
on MLP using perceptron learning was an
essentially interactive combinatorial
optimization problem, all research on
the topic stalled for over a decade. It
was many years before the nest
breakthrough.
Now the reason for the problem is that
the perceptron with a threshold
activation is a flat function with zero
derivative everywhere except at zero
where it's non- differentiable. Now this
means you cannot easily determine how to
adjust the parameters of your model. So
consider this example. This is a binary
classification task on a single uh
input.
So uh the uh function I these are the
training samples
and here are the outputs ideal outputs
for the training samples. These two
instances must be classified as zero.
These three must be classified as one.
And the actual
classification function over the entire
training data that you'd like to learn
is this guy. Okay.
Now let's say your network currently
computes this other function. This one
given by this dotted line. So is the
network perfect or does it make errors?
Is the network making errors? And if so,
how many?
How many errors are we making? makes two
errors, right? So, but the network says
that this is the threshold. Anything to
the right is being classified as one.
Anything to the left is being classified
as zero. Now, let's say I find that it's
making errors. So, I try adjusting the
network. I shift the threshold all the
way out here. So, that the
function is now like this.
Has the number of errors changed?
Okay. So I shift it the other way all
the way out here so that the function is
now like this. Has the number of errors
changed?
No. So after all that movement, am I
able to determine whether I should be
moving the threshold right or left?
No. Right? And so that's the problem
over here. When you have a
non-ifferiable function,
the uh fact that is that the threshold
has to be moved left. But small
perturbations will not give you this
information. This is the same in higher
dimensions too. Like here the perceptron
or the threshold activation is a flat
function with zero derivative everywhere
except at this boundary. So if you
compose the entire
compose a a perceptron for instance to
to learn to classify these these data
these red and blue data and if your
current classifier is given by this blue
line I could rotate change the weights
and rotate the classifier all the way to
this red line or all the way to this red
line and the error would not change. And
so I have no indication that whether I
should continue this way or whether I
should continue this way to reduce the
error because the function is has zero
derivative everywhere. That making
sense?
Yes. No. Right. So how does the
derivatives makes make a difference?
because the derivative says how much the
output changes how much the error
changes in response to a small change of
input and here the derivative is zero.
So which is why you can't say whether
you know which way to go. Did that
answer your question
to the person who has a question? How
does the derivative matter?
Okay.
So
how
do we and so you know this only gets
worse when you get on more complex
situations like this when you try to
learn a classifier for this example
individual neurons weights can change a
lot without changing the overall error
and this happens because the overall MLP
itself is a flat non-ifferiable function
meaning it has derivative zero
derivative almost everywhere and in the
few places where it does have
derivatives at the various edges the
derivative is infinite
So uh this which means that perturbing
the parameters is not going to give you
any indication of whether you're going
in the right direction. So we must come
up with a solution. We're going to
change the way of computing the mismatch
such that the modif such that modifying
the classifier slightly lets us know if
you're going in the right way or not.
This requires changing both our
activation function and the manner in
which we evaluate the mismatch between
the classifier output and the target
output. Our mismatch function will now
now no longer actually count errors but
is a proxy for it. So to do this we make
the neuron differentiable with nonzero
derivatives over much of the input space
which means that rather than using the
threshold activation we we're going to
use activation functions like these
which have non-zero derivative and are
not flat
that that way when you change the
weights even a little bit this will
change result in a change of the output
even if the classification boundary
itself doesn't cross a training instance
and we'll get an idea of whether a
particular incremental change to the
weights improves the classifier or makes
it worse. So to understand this better,
let's consider this example again of one
dimensional data. Here are the input to
a single uh scalar x. The target output
which is the the target output which is
the class label is either zero or one.
The blue dots are from the zero class.
The red dots are from the one class. In
the upper two panels, I'm comparing two
different threshold activations.
In the left panel, the threshold is T1.
In the right one, the threshold is T2.
In both cases, you have one red dot
classified, mclassified. So there is
one. So say you had an initial guess of
T1 for the threshold and then adjusted
it all the way to T2. By simply counting
the errors, can you say if you're
shifting the threshold in the correct
direction or not? Can you say just by sh
just by moving the threshold to theta?
No. Right? Because the errors didn't
change.
Now in the lower panel I have a
different kind of activation shown by
this smooth curve over here.
here
uh the activation goes smoothly from 0
to one like so. Now I'm going to assign
a class label of one if the activation
value exceeds.5
and I'm going to assign a class label of
zero if the activation value goes below
0.5. How many errors is this classifier
making in both cases?
How many how many errors is the
classifier making over here? It's still
making one error. But then instead of
simply counting whether an instance has
been mclassified,
I'm going to look at how much the target
value is off from the curve which is
given by the length of these dotted
lines. And so when you look at the
length of these dotted lines, if I take
the total length of these dotted lines,
where is it lower? the figure to the
left or the figure to the right?
>> Where is the globe? To the right. Right.
And if the classifier were perfect,
would the uh would the length of the
dotted lines be high or is it going to
be small?
It's going to be small. And so based on
this, the fact that the total length of
the dotted lines is smaller to the
figure to the right, do we know which
way to move the function?
So,
and which way would we move it based on
this?
We would move it right because moving it
right reduces the total length of the
function, right? And so
this you'll so from from the total
length you're able to compute that the
total length decreased as you move the
function right. And so you know that
continuing to shift shift it uh uh
right
>> it's to the left isn't it?
>> It's got to be shifted left right. So
continuing to shift it left is the right
thing to be doing. Right. So in
derivative terms we'll find that the
derivative of this total length with
respect to a left shift is negative.
That is if you shift the threshold left
the length increases which is what you
want. And this is a consequence of the
fact that the activation function itself
has non-zero derivative. Now at any x
you can compute if the function
decreases or increases if you shift it.
So I know I sort of uh got mixed up a
bit but did this makes did this make
sense that the fact that we are looking
at the total length and we are we are
sort of saying that shifting the curve
left this is actually shifted the curve
left reduces the total length and so
shifting it left is the right thing to
do.
That make sense to all of you? Right.
Okay. And so that's basically what we're
going to do. Now I have the next poll
for this which is my longest poll. Let
me release this poll.
Okay, 15 seconds, guys.
10 seconds.
It's a long
poll. So,
okay, I'll end it here
and let's go through it guys. Right. So
this first statement true or false this
one true or false false
the threshold activation
true the second one true or false
third one true or false
okay with respect to the continuous
activation.
So this first statement true or false.
Second one true or false.
Third one
also true. Okay. So let's see. You're
right.
You know increasing or decreasing the
threshold will not change the overall
classification error unless the
threshold moves past a mclassified
training sample. So you cannot know if a
change of the threshold moves it in the
correct direction. Whereas for the
continuous activation, shifting the
function may not change the overall
classification error, but it's still
going to change the total distance of
the value of the function from the
target value. And so the derivative of
the total distance with respect to the
shift gives us an indication of which
direction to shift the function to
improve the classification error.
Now that's what we're going to use. But
there are two key requirements for
learnability for this to work. First the
activation function must be continuously
varying and differentiable. Second our
error function or divergence must also
be differentiable. Let's look at this
first guy. Right.
So we're going to replace this threshold
activation function of the perceptron
with a continuous graded function like
the relu or the soft or the sigmoid.
These activations are all differentiable
and have derivatives almost everywhere.
And even at locations where they do
where they're not differentiable like
this corner for a loop, they are still
continuous and have what are called sub
derivatives which are bounds on the
derivatives that behave like derivatives
for our purpose. So we'll discuss sub
derivatives in a later class. Now of
these different activations the sigmoid
activation which we which we discussed
in some detail in the last class is uh
special it's given by this formula over
here 1 / 1 + e raus z as the aine value
z goes from minus infinity to infinity
the function goes smoothly from 0 to 1
we saw how the math works in the last
class the shape of the function itself
as a curve like this it has a very nice
interpretation
the output of the sigmoid can be viewed
as the probability that the input is
from class one that is it is can be
viewed as interpreted as P of Y= 1 given
X when this is low you can assume the
input to belong to class zero if it's
high you can assume it's one there's a
somewhat more detailed explanation of
the intuition behind this of the slides
I'll skip it I'll leave it as readings
please go through the slides because the
explanation will figure in today's quiz
but then let's move on right So we'll
we'll return to the fact that
perceptrons with sigmoid activations
usually mind class probabilities in a
later lecture.
But moving on. So here's what we have
the activation sigma of Z. If it's a
differentiable function of Z, then what
it means is that sigma prime of Z has a
nonzero value, which means I know how
much a small how a small perturbation of
Z will change by. But then Z is an
aphine function of X which means you
know it's a it's a weighted sum of all
of these X's and that's differentiable.
So I also know how perturbing this W
will change Z. So change chaining it up
I now know how perturbing W will change
Y because I know how perturbing W
changes Z and I know how perturbing Z
changes Y. And so now I'm actually able
to compute the changes in the output of
the perceptron for small changes in
either the inputs or the wave.
Now the overall network when the
is a network of perceptrons and each
perceptron is differentiable with
respect to its weights, its biases and
also its inputs. When a perceptron is
differentiable, it means you can
explicitly compute how the output
changes in response to small
perturbations of its inputs and weights
and you can compute the entire chain of
such responses. So we can figure out how
small changes of say this weight w will
affect the output of this perceptron
because this activation function is
differentiable. But then we can also
because
all the activations are differentiable.
We can also figure out how small
perturbations of this guy will change
the outputs of these perceptrons.
And in turn we can figure out how small
perturbations of these guys will output
Y. So combining them all we can figure
out how small perturbations of W will
change Y.
That is we can compute the derivative of
the output of the network with respect
to this weight. In fact this holds for
every parameter of the network. The
overall function represented by the
network is differentiable with respect
to every parameter of the network using
the chain rule which means small changes
in any of these parameters result in
measurable changes in the output and we
can compute this change. And so for non-
thresholding activation functions
uh where the derivatives are not zero,
these derivatives are generally non zero
for most inputs. And we can actually
derive these derivatives using the chain
rule as we'll see later. But the key
point is that being able to compute this
derivatives tells me how much changing
any particular parameter changes the
output.
Now that leads to the second
requirement. You want the error function
to also be differentiable.
Remember that in order to optimize the
network, we had to define a divergence
function that quantifies the gap between
the network output and the target
function. And for classification
problems,
this divergence function is not a
classification error but a proxy to it.
As we saw, we also saw that the
divergence function should have the
following properties. If f and g are
identical, if g equals f, the divergence
must be zero. When the two are not
identical, the divergence must always be
positive. We are adding this requirement
that the divergence is differentiable
with respect to f, which is the output
of the network.
Combining the two,
we the output of the network was
differentiable with respect to the
network parameter. So we know how how
much perturbing this parameter will
change the output. The divergence in
term in turn is differentiable with
respect to the output of the network. So
we know how much perturbing this guy
this guy Y will perturb the divergence.
So combining combining them all we will
know how much chain perturbing this
weight w a little bit will perturb the
divergence. And we can now use this to
adjust the parameters of the network.
So that did that make sense to all of
you guys?
That makes sense to all of you guys.
I have one a single yes. We're going to
get a lot more into the details of this.
I'm just conveying the concepts out
here. Right. So
how do we learn the network?
Recall that the network is modeling a
function. For example, this guy, right?
And and using any particular value of
this uh network parameters, you can get
some other function like this one. And
what we actually want to do is to
minimize this shaded area.
For this we define the divergence
between these two guys and integrate the
divergence over the entire input.
But then we'll make a minor
modification. Suppose you know for for
through some a priority uh knowledge
that the input never falls in this range
and it never falls in this range. Then
should you be spending any effort
minimizing the error in these regions or
can we ignore them?
What do you guys think?
We should ignore them. Right? So more
generally,
you don't want to be expending any
effort in regions that don't matter.
So
uh we will be more conservative in
general since you're only guaranteed to
be approximating the true function. It's
better to focus on input values the
values of Z that really matter. Now not
all inputs are possible and so and some
inputs are more possible than others. So
instead of just minimizing the error
blindly at each X we are going to assign
an importance of that X where the
importance is all about how frequently
that X occurs in real life and that is
given by the probability of X itself.
And so this modified error function
looks like this where where you're not
merely integrating the divergence but
you're waiting the divergence by the
probability of x itself.
Is this making sense what we did over
here?
This making sense to you guys?
Yes or no?
Right. So P of X is the probability of
X. It tells you how frequently X
happens. So things X's that have more
happen more frequently,
their divergences are more important
than X's that happen less frequently.
That's what this is. Did that explain
it?
So if an X never happens,
we're just saying we're not calculating
P of X. This is what we actually want to
minimize. We speaking, remember we are
speaking of the weighted shaded area.
Did that answer your question? Earlier
we said we wanted to minimize the shaded
area. Now we added a waiting term.
Right? P of X is the probability of X.
When you integrating there's always the
D of X, right? This is a standard
integral formula.
Did that answer your question?
This shaded area is the integral of the
divergence
with respect to x. But I'm also I'm also
waiting each x by the probability of x.
Did that answer your question? Yes or
no?
I'm assuming it did. Okay. So, let me
continue. So, any questions here guys?
If not, just moving on.
In reality, of course, you can't compute
this integral because we don't have g of
x everywhere.
What we have instead are samples of g of
x as we saw training data uh xy pair xy
pairs pairs of input and uh output. And
so what we really do is we are as we saw
earlier we just compute the average
divergence between the uh actual output
of the network and the desired output of
the network. And this is going to be our
approximation approxy for this guy.
Again we had this target function. We
had the actual function computed by the
network
and we wanted to minimize the shaded
area except that at each point
weed the x by the probability of x.
That's because you want to focus most of
your modeling on the most important
components of x. So this is what you
actually want to minimize.
This is what you will act you will
minimize in practice.
And our hope is that this guy is the
same as this guy. Now this integral over
here is in fact the expected value of
the divergence of X. How many of you are
familiar with the term expected value,
right? We don't determine P of X. All
I'm saying is what we want to minimize
is the expected value of the divergence
of X. Right?
We can't compute it. Instead, we're
computing the average divergence over
the entire training set. But then it
just so happens that the average
expectation
of the average divergence
summation dive
is 1 / n. The summation of the
expectation of the divergence.
And so the expectation of the divergence
is just a value. There are n of these,
right? So that's going to be 1 / n * n *
the expect expectation of the divergence
which is simply going to be the
expectation of the divergence itself. So
what this means is that
you know crazy math apart this average
divergence statistically speaking is
what is called an unbiased estimator of
the expected divergence. And the
expected divergence of course is this
weighted shaded area, right? And so
uh you know to state it differently, if
I ran this experiment millions of times
where each time I got a bunch of end
training samples from the of the data
and then computed the average training
average uh uh divergence over all of
these guys, the average the of those
averages is in fact going to be the
shaded area itself. That's what the math
tells us. And so this is the excuse that
we use to use this average divergence as
the objective that we minimize rather
than this guy which we which we which we
can't really compute because we neither
have P of X nor G of X.
Did that make sense to you guys?
Right?
We don't really have P of X. We don't
have G. But then the you know in
expectation this guy is the same as this
guy and so this is what we will minimize
and this of course is our empirical risk
right and so this whole thing is what we
will call this business of training is
what we will call empirical risk
minimization
is an instance of empirical risk
minimization. We are given a bunch of
training input output pairs and we
define a divergence between the actual
output of the network and the desired
output of the network. We compute the
average divergence over the training
data and we learn the parameters of the
network to minimize this average
divergence. And this average divergence
if we that we compute we will actually
call this a loss. This is the
terminology you repeatedly encounter in
this course and in the deep learning
literature. Again, keep in mind that
this loss is an estimate for this guy.
The loss is actually some kind of an
estimate for the shaded area. It's not
actually the shaded area. What we want
to minimize is the weighted shaded area,
but the loss is an estimate of it and
it's an estimate for the expected
divergence and this is what we will
minimize. The loss is an unbiased
estimate of the expected divergence
which is why we assume that minimizing
it will also minimize the expected
divergence. The key point to note is
that since our training set is given and
thus fixed, the only variable over here
that can be modified is W. And so the
losses function is a function only of
the network parameters W. And so here's
the overall problem statement.
Given a bunch of training instances, we
define a loss which is the average
divergence over the training data. It's
a function of the network parameters. We
will try to find the network parameters
W that minimize this guy. This is a
problem of function minimization of
optimization. And so the story so far we
learn networks by fitting them to
training instances drawn for target
function learning networks of threshold
activation perceptrons requests of
solving a hard combinatorial
optimization problem. Instead we use
continuous activation functions with
non-zero derivatives to enable us to
estimate network parameters. We define a
differentiable divergence between the
output of the network and the desired
output of the training instances. And
then we optimize network parameters to
minimize this error. This is an instance
of function minimization. So I will stop
right here. I apologize for going over
by 2 minutes. And I